{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "8.1","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["2% iodine and then 70% alcohol solution","70% alcohol and then 2% iodine or an iodophor","70% alcohol and then 95% alcohol","95% alcohol only"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "70% alcohol and then 2% iodine or an iodophor","explanation": "To attain asepsis of the skin, 70% alcohol followed by 2% iodine is used for obtaining blood cultures"},"question": "The aseptic collection of blood cultures requires that the skin be cleansed with:","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Specimen collection/1"},{"choices": ["10 seconds","30 seconds","60 seconds","5 minutes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "60 seconds","explanation": "The iodine should remain on the skin for 1 minute because instant antisepsis does not occur when cleansing the skin for a blood culture"},"question": "When cleansing the skin with alcohol and then iodine for the collection of a blood culture, the iodine (or iodophor) should remain intact on the skin for at least:","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Specimen collection and handling/1"},{"choices": ["It inhibits phagocytosis and complement","It promotes formation of a blood clot","It enhances growth of anaerobes","It functions as a preservative"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "It inhibits phagocytosis and complement","explanation": "SPS is used in most commercial blood culture products because it functions as an anticoagulant and prevents phagocytosis and complement activation. In addition, SPS neutralizes aminoglycoside antibiotics. Addition of SPS may inhibit some Neisseria and Peptostreptococcus, but this can be reversed with 1.2% gelatin"},"question": "What is the purpose of adding 0.025% to 0.050% sodium polyanethol sulfonate (SPS) to nutrient broth media for the collection of blood cultures?","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Media/1"},{"choices": ["Staphylococcus aureus","Streptococcus pneumoniae","Corynebacterium diphtheriae","Bacteroides fragilis"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Corynebacterium diphtheriae","explanation": "C. diphtheriae must be recovered from the deep layers of the pseudomembrane that forms in the nasopharyngeal area. A flexible calcium alginate nasopharyngeal swab is the best choice for collecting a specimen from the posterior nares and pharynx"},"question": "A flexible calcium alginate nasopharyngeal swab is the collection device of choice for recovery of which organism from the nasopharynx?","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedure/Specimen collection and handling/1"},{"choices": ["Neisseria gonorrhoeae","Enterobacteriaceae","Campylobacter fetus","Streptococcus pneumoniae"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Neisseria gonorrhoeae","explanation": "Specimens for culture of N. gonorrhoeae are best if plated immediately or transported in a medium containing activated charcoal to absorb inhibitory substances that hinder their recovery from the specimens"},"question": "Semisolid transport media, such as Amies, Stuart, or Cary-Blair, are suitable for the transport of swabs for culture of most pathogens except:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Specimen collection and handling/2"},{"choices": ["Cotton fiber swab of the abscess area","Skin snip of the surface tissue","Needle aspirate after surface decontamination","Swab of the scalpel used for débridement"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Needle aspirate after surface decontamination","explanation": "Anaerobic specimens are easily contaminated with organisms present on the skin or mucosal surfaces when a swab is used. Needle aspiration of an abscess following surface decontamination provides the least exposure to ambient oxygen"},"question": "Select the method of choice for recovery of anaerobic bacteria from a deep abscess.","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Specimen collection and handling/2"},{"choices": ["MacConkey, blood, birdseed, and Campylobacter (Campy) agars","Hektoen, MacConkey, MacConkey-Sorbitol, Campy blood, colistin–nalidixic acid (CNA) agars; Selenite-F broth (SEL)","CNA and Christensen urea agars and thioglycollate media","Blood, Campy, Mueller-Hinton agars, and thioglycollate media"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hektoen, MacConkey, MacConkey-Sorbitol, Campy blood, colistin–nalidixic acid (CNA) agars; Selenite-F broth (SEL)","explanation": "Hektoen agar selectively isolates pathogenic coliforms, especially Salmonella and Shigella. MacConkey agar differentiates lactose fermenters from nonfermenters. MacConkey with sorbitol isolates Escherichia coli 0157:H7. CNA agar contains antibiotics that prohibit growth of gram-negative coliforms but not gram-positive cocci. Campy blood agar contains the antibiotics cephalothin, trimethoprim, vancomycin, polymyxin B, and amphotericin B to prevent growth of Enterobacteriaceae, Pseudomonas spp., and fungi"},"question": "Select the primary and differential media of choice for recovery of most fecal pathogens.","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Stool culture/2"},{"choices": ["MacConkey agar and thioglycollate media","Thiosulfate–citrate–bile–sucrose (TCBS) agar and alkaline peptone water (APW) broth","Blood agar and SEL broth","CNA agar"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Thiosulfate–citrate–bile–sucrose (TCBS) agar and alkaline peptone water (APW) broth","explanation": "TCBS agar is used to grow V. cholerae, which appear as yellow colonies as a result of the use of both citrate and sucrose. APW is used as an enrichment broth and should be subcultured to TCBS agar for further evaluation of Vibrio colonies"},"question": "Select the media of choice for recovery of Vibrio cholerae from a stool specimen.","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Stool culture/2"},{"choices": ["Neisseria species","Enterobacteriaceae","Pseudomonas aeruginosa","Staphylococcus aureus"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Staphylococcus aureus","explanation": "CNA agar inhibits the growth of gram-negative bacteria and is used to isolate gram-positive cocci from specimens. This medium is especially useful for stool and wound cultures because these may contain large numbers of gram-negative rods"},"question": "CNA agar is used primarily for the recovery of:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Gram-positive cocci/2"},{"choices": ["Sheep", "Horses", "Humans", "Dogs"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Sheep","explanation": "Sheep RBCs are used in blood agar plates because they are readily available and less inhibitory than cells of other species. The type of hemolysis is determined by the source of RBCs. Sheep RBCs are chosen because of the characteristically clear hemolysis produced by β-hemolytic streptococci, Staphylococcus, and other pathogens producing β-hemolysins. Sheep blood does not support the growth of Haemophilus haemolyticus, eliminating the possibility of confusing it with β-hemolytic streptococci in throat cultures"},"question": "In the United States, most blood agar plates are prepared with 5% or 10% red blood cells (RBCs) obtained from:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Culture/1"},{"choices": ["Transport the genital swab in charcoal transport medium","Plate the specimen directly on modified Thayer-Martin (MTM) medium","Plate the specimen directly on New York City or Martin-Lewis agar","Culture specimens in ambient oxygen at 37°C"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Culture specimens in ambient oxygen at 37°C","explanation": "MTM, New York City, and Martin-Lewis agars contain blood factors needed to support the growth of N. gonorrhoeae as well as antibiotics that prevent growth of normal genital flora. Cultures must be incubated in 3% to 7% carbon dioxide (CO2) at 35°C. Cultures should be held a minimum of 48 hours before being considered negative"},"question": "All of the following are appropriate when attempting to isolate N. gonorrhoeae from a genital specimen except:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Culture/1"},{"choices": ["Haemophilus spp. and Neisseria spp., respectively","Haemophilus spp. and N. gonorrhoeae, respectively","Neisseria spp. and Streptococcus spp., respectively","Streptococcus spp. and Staphylococcus spp., respectively"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Haemophilus spp. and N. gonorrhoeae, respectively","explanation": "Chocolate agar provides X factor (hemin) and V factor (nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide [NAD]) required for the growth of Haemophilus spp. Thayer-Martin medium is a chocolate agar containing the antibiotics that permit isolation of N. gonorrhoeae in specimens containing large numbers of gram-negative bacteria, including commensal Neisseria spp"},"question": "Chocolate agar and MTM agar are used for the recovery of:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Stool culture/2"},{"choices": ["Yersinia enterocolitica","Yersinia intermedia","Clostridium perfringens","Clostridium difficile"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Clostridium difficile","explanation": "CCFA is used for recovery of C. difficile from stool cultures. Cycloserine and cefoxitin inhibit growth of gram-negative coliforms in the stool specimen. C. difficile ferments fructose, forming acid that, in the presence of neutral red, causes the colonies to become yellow"},"question": "Cycloserine–cefoxitin–fructose agar (CCFA) is used for the recovery of:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Stool culture/1"},{"choices": ["Enterobacteriaceae","Enterococcus spp.","Staphylococcus spp.","Neisseria spp."],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Enterobacteriaceae","explanation": "DCA inhibits gram-positive organisms. N. gonorrhoeae and Neisseria meningitidis are too fastidious to grow on DCA. Citrate and deoxycholate salts inhibit growth of gram-positive bacteria. The media contain lactose and neutral red, allowing differentiation of lactose fermenters (pink colonies) from nonfermenters (colorless)"},"question": "Deoxycholate agar (DCA) is useful for the isolation of:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Stool culture/1"},{"choices": ["Staphylococcus spp. from normal flora","Yersinia spp. that do not grow on Hektoen agar","Enterobacteriaceae from gastrointestinal specimens","Streptococcus spp. from stool cultures"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Enterobacteriaceae from gastrointestinal specimens","explanation": "XLD agar is selective for gram-negative coliforms because of a high concentration (0.25%) of deoxycholate, which inhibits gram-positive bacteria. In addition, XLD is differential for Shigella and Salmonella spp. The medium contains xylose, lactose, and sucrose, which are fermented by most normal intestinal coliforms producing yellow colonies. Shigella does not ferment the sugars and produces red (or clear) colonies. Salmonella spp. ferment xylose; however, they also decarboxylate lysine in the medium, causing production of ammonia. Therefore, Salmonella first appear yellow but become red. Some Salmonella produce hydrogen sulfide (H2S) from sodium thiosulfate and therefore appear as red colonies with black centers"},"question": "Xylose lysine deoxycholate (XLD) agar is a highly selective medium used for the recovery of which bacteria?","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Stool culture/1"},{"choices": ["β-Hemolytic streptococci and coagulase-positive staphylococci","Haemophilus influenzae and Haemophilus parainfluenzae","Proteus spp. and Escherichia coli","Pseudomonas spp. and Acinetobacter spp."],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Haemophilus influenzae and Haemophilus parainfluenzae","explanation": "Both gram-positive cocci and gram-negative bacilli will grow on blood agar plates, but the medium is used in conjunction with a selective medium, such as CNA agar, for gram-positive cocci and MacConkey agar for gram-negative bacilli. H. influenzae requires X and V factors, and H. parainfluenzae requires V factor; the primary isolation medium for Haemophilus is chocolate agar"},"question": "A sheep blood agar plate is used as a primary isolation medium when all of the following organisms are to be recovered from a wound specimen except:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Wound culture/2"},{"choices": ["Mycobacterium marinum and Mycobacterium avium intracellulare","Bacteroides, Peptostreptococcus, and Clostridium spp.","Proteus spp.","Enterococcus spp."],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Bacteroides, Peptostreptococcus, and Clostridium spp.","explanation": "Anaerobic culture media can be prereduced before sterilization by boiling, saturation with oxygen-free gas, and addition of cysteine or other thiol compounds. The final oxidation reduction potential (Eh) of the medium should be approximately –150 mV to minimize the effects of exposure of organisms to oxygen during inoculation"},"question": "Prereduced and vitamin K1-supplemented blood agar plates are recommended isolation media for:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Anaerobes/2"},{"choices": ["Obtain urethral, cervical swabs and urine specimens placed in transport media for the direct detection of antigen or nucleic acid and/or culture","Plate onto blood and chocolate agar","Inoculate into thioglycollate (THIO) broth","Plate onto MTM agar within 24 hours"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Obtain urethral, cervical swabs and urine specimens placed in transport media for the direct detection of antigen or nucleic acid and/or culture","explanation": "Chlamydiae are strict intracellular organisms and must be cultured using living cells (e.g., cyclohexamide-treated McCoy cells). Direct smears can also be made at the time of culture. Fluorescein-conjugated monoclonal antibodies may be used to identify the organisms in infected cells. Cell cultures present limitations but are used if legal situations (e.g., sexual abuse) are implied. Commercially available kits for antigen detection and nucleic acid amplification and hybridization techniques, which have been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA), are not culture methods but appear more reliable for the detection of infection in individuals who are symptomatic and shedding large numbers of organisms"},"question": "Which procedure(s) is (are) appropriate for the diagnosis of Chlamydia spp. infections when using genital specimens?","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Virus culture/1"},{"choices": ["Antibiotics and 5% sheep blood","Saline and 5% sheep blood","22% bovine albumin","Antibiotics and protein nutrient"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Antibiotics and protein nutrient","explanation": "Media for transporting specimens for virus culture include Hanks balanced salt solution with bovine albumin, Amies media, Stuart transport media, and Leibovitz-Emory media. Media used for transporting specimens for viral culture are similar to those for bacteria with the addition of a nutrient, such as fetal calf serum or albumin, and antibiotics. Specimens should be refrigerated (not frozen) after being placed in the transport media until the culture media can be inoculated"},"question": "Specimens for virus culture should be transported in media containing:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Virus culture/1"},{"choices": ["Refrigerated at 4°C to 6°C","Frozen at –20°C","Stored at room temperature for no longer than 24 hours","Incubated at 37°C and cultured as soon as possible"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Incubated at 37°C and cultured as soon as possible","explanation": "Fastidious organisms, such as Neisseria and Haemophilus, frequently isolated from the CSF of patients with bacterial meningitis are preserved by placing the fluid in 3% to 7% CO2 at 35°C to 37°C (or at room temperature for no longer than 30 minutes), if the specimen cannot be cultured immediately"},"question": "Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) should be cultured immediately, but if delayed, the specimen should be:","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Specimen collection and transport/1"},{"choices": ["Chromogenic cephalosporin","Penicillin","Oxidase","Chloramphenicol acetyltransferase"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Chromogenic cephalosporin","explanation": "β-Lactamase production by bacteria that are resistant to penicillin and cephalosporin is detected using one of these drugs as a substrate. Penicillin is hydrolyzed by β-lactamase into acidic products that can be detected as a color change by a pH indicator. In the iodometric method, a disk containing a penicillin–starch substrate turns blue when a drop of iodine is added. The most sensitive method of detection is based on the ability of the organism to hydrolyze the β-lactam ring of a chromogenic cephalosporin (e.g., nitrocefin), which is used as the substrate. A positive test indicates the organism’s resistance to penicillin, ampicillin, amoxicillin, carbenicillin, mezlocillin, and piperacillin"},"question": "The most sensitive method for the detection of β-lactamase in bacteria is by the use of:","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Sensitivity testing/2"},{"choices": ["The amount needed to cause bacteriostasis","A minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 16 μg/mL or greater","An MIC of 64 μg/mL or greater","The optimal therapeutic level of drug that is achievable in serum"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The optimal therapeutic level of drug that is achievable in serum","explanation": "The term breakpoint refers to an antimicrobial concentration in the serum associated with optimal therapy using the customary dosing schedule. An organism is susceptible if the MIC is at or below the breakpoint"},"question": "The breakpoint of an antimicrobial drug refers to:","reference": "Microbiology/Apply principle of theory and practice related to laboratory operations/Sensitivity testing/2"},{"choices": ["Inoculum size","Incubation time","Growth rate of the bacteria","All of these options"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All of these options","explanation": "In vitro testing of drugs is reliable if the method is standardized. In addition to the first three variables, the type of media and the stability of antibiotics affect the results of MIC testing and must be carefully controlled"},"question": "Which of the following variables may change the results of an MIC?","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Sensitivity testing/2"},{"choices": ["The swarming area should be ignored","The results of the disk diffusion method are invalid","The swarming area should be measured as the growth boundary","The isolate should be retested after diluting to a 0.05 McFarland standard"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The swarming area should be ignored","explanation": "A thin film of growth appearing in the zone area of inhibition around the susceptibility disk should be ignored when swarming Proteus or other organisms are encountered. Discontinuous, poor growth or tiny colonies near the end of the zone should also be ignored"},"question": "According to the Kirby-Bauer standard antimicrobial susceptibility testing method, what should be done when interpreting the zone size of a motile, swarming organism, such as a Proteus species?","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Sensitivity testing/2"},{"choices": ["Cephalosporins","Penicillins","Tetracyclines","Aminoglycosides"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Aminoglycosides","explanation": "The aminoglycoside antibiotics are bactericidal agents that act by inhibiting protein synthesis. They show a low incidence of bacterial resistance but must be monitored carefully because at high doses they can cause ototoxicity and nephrotoxicity. The group includes amikacin, gentamicin, tobramycin, kanamycin, streptomycin, and spectinomycin. These drugs are usually administered intravenously or intramuscularly because they are poorly absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract"},"question": "Which class of antibiotics is used for the treatment of serious gram-negative infections as well as infections with Mycobacterium tuberculosis?","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Antibiotics/1"},{"choices": ["Hektoen agar","Cefsulodin–irgasan–novobiocin (CIN) agar","Blood agar","Eosin methylene blue agar"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Cefsulodin–irgasan–novobiocin (CIN) agar","explanation": "CIN agar inhibits the growth of many organisms from the family Enterobacteriaceae. Yersinia spp. are also recovered from MacConkey and Salmonella-Shigella agars. Y. enterocolitica are seen as “bull’s eye” colonies on CIN agar after 48 hours at room temperature"},"question": "Select the medium best suited for the recovery of Y. enterocolitica from a patient with gastroenteritis.","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Gram-negative bacilli/2"},{"choices": ["Collection of multiple sets of blood culture specimens","Incubation of blood cultures at both 28°C and 35°C","Culture aspirates from bubos to MacConkey agar at room temperature","All of these options"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All of these options","explanation": "Y. pestis is on the list of agents of bioterrorism. Isolation and identification should be performed in a facility with a Level II or higher biosafety rating. If there is a high risk of aerosolizing the specimen during processing, procedures should be performed under Level III biosafety conditions. Recovery of Y. pestis is highest if the specimen is cultured within 2 hours of collection"},"question": "A suspected case of plague requires which of the following procedures to confirm Yersinia pestis?","reference": "Microbiology/Apply knowledge of procedures/Gram-negative bacilli/2"},{"choices": ["Aeromonas hydrophilia","Escherichia coli","Salmonella spp.","Shigella spp."],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Aeromonas hydrophilia","explanation": "The oxidase positive test result rules out the members of the Enterobacteriaceae family. Colonies of A. hydrophilia and Plesiomonas spp. (both oxidase positive) might be mistaken for Vibrio spp. because all three grow as clear colonies on MacConkey agar, are β-hemolytic on blood agar, and are oxidase positive. Aeromonas spp. will also grow on CNN agar and mimic Y. enterocolitica (a member of the Enterobacteriaceae family and oxidase negative)"},"question": "SITUATION: Abdominal pain, fever, vomiting, and nausea prompted an older male to seek medical attention. A watery stool specimen producing no fecal leukocytes or erythrocytes was cultured, and it grew a predominance of gram-negative fermentative bacilli. The colonies were β-hemolytic on blood agar and cream colored on MacConkey agar. The colonies were both oxidase and catalase positive. What is the most likely identification?","reference": "Microbiology/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Gram-negative bacilli/3"},{"choices": ["Mannitol fermentation, Na+ requirement","Oxidase, motility","Oxidase, nitrate","Hemolysis on blood agar, catalase"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Mannitol fermentation, Na+ requirement","explanation": "All three organisms are positive for oxidase production and are motile. Plesiomonas spp. do not grow on TCBS agar. Clear colonies on MacConkey agar and yellow colonies on TCBS agar indicate Vibrio or Aeromonas spp. However, only Vibrio spp. require Na+ (1% NaCl) in the medium for growth. Vibrio Aeromonas Plesiomonas Oxidase + + + Na+ requirement + Neg Neg Mannitol fermentation + + Neg Growth onTCBS + + Ne"},"question": "SITUATION: Several attendees of a medical conference in the Gulf coast area became ill after frequenting a seafood restaurant. A presumptive identification of V. cholerae was made after stool specimens from several subjects grew clear colonies on MacConkey agar and yellow colonies on TCBS agar. Which key tests would help eliminate Aeromonas and Plesiomonas spp.?","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Gram-negative bacilli/3"},{"choices": ["Xylose lysine deoxycholate agar","MacConkey agar","MacConkey agar with sorbitol","Hektoen agar"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "MacConkey agar with sorbitol","explanation": "E. coli 0157:H7 ferments lactose and, therefore, appears as dark pink colonies on MacConkey agar. To differentiate E. coli 0157:H7 from normal fecal flora, MacConkey agar with sorbitol is used. E. coli 0157:H7 does not ferment sorbitol, and usually are colorless colonies"},"question": "SITUATION: A group of elementary students became ill after eating undercooked ground beef prepared in the school cafeteria. The suspected pathogen, E. coli serotype 0157:H7, is usually recovered using which of the following media?","reference": "Microbiology/Select methods/Reagents/Media/Gram-negative bacilli/2"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Specimen Collection, Media, and Methods"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}